### Guilherme Silveira dos Santos

Berlin, DE xguiga@gmail.com

Phone: +49 (173) 979-9383

#### Summary

I'm a Computer Engineer since 2011 but I started programming long time before that. I consider myself a self learner, who is always looking for new technologies and usually my learning process is very quick. I have started to study PHP at home since I was teenager what gave me good knowledge to develop several web applications. During the college and internships I learned other programming languages, such as C, C++, Java and Lua and of course could improve myself with other skills.

I've been working for long time as a freelancer developer and most of the time involving web development, as a result I became an experienced web developer with big expertise in PHP, JavaScript, CSS and HTML. Apart from that I improved myself as DevOps creating CLI and scripts to automate deploys, configure servers, etc. In 2015 I started working with Go.

I've already contributed in many open source projects like Enlightenment Foundation Libraries (EFL), Zend Framework, Elastic (Elasticsearch client fo Go) and other small libraries in Go, PHP and JavaScript. I really like to work with open source projects and I usually do it in my spare time. In the last few years testing (e.g. unit tests, TDD) became part of my process of development which is code, test, deploy and monitor.

I worked in companies with several different technologies and it made me an open minded developer, with can-do attitude and a good interpersonal relationship. Currently I'm working mainly with Go as Senior Software Engineer in Berlin, but always looking for a new challenges.

#### Education

UNIVALI University, BSc in Computer Engineering, June 2011.

# Experience

# **ProShare**

Nov 2019 - Present

 $Senior\ Software\ Engineer$ 

Main Technologies: Go, gRPC, MariaDB, GraphQL, Docker, AWS, Kubernetes;

Develop a whole platform for car sharing focused in professionals from scratch. Go was the only language in the backend, and so far MariaDB was choose as database based in our use cases. All internal communication were done through gRPC but it was also our public API. Because some clients are not easy to integrate to gRPC it was created a thin RESTful API layer on the top of gRPC. We also provide a GraphQL API which also was a layer on the top of our gRPC API.

All infrastructure were written using Terraform running in a Kubernetes cluster on AWS.

# Experience

### DeliveryHero (foodora/foodpanda)

Jan 2018 - Nov 2019

Senior Software Engineer

Main Technologies: Go, ElasticSearch, MySQL, Redis, Docker, AWS, Kubernetes;

I was working on Pandora platform (Foodora + Foodpanda), moving from monolithic application to micro-services using even-driven architecture. Member of Search & Discovery team, I was building the service to handle the search for 4 different brands in 20 different countries. Also I helped them to develop a new open source library. One of my task was also help them to define new guidelines and best practices for Go projects to level the whole Pandora team.

### Experience

### Ridelink

Sep 2016 - Dec 2017

Technical Lead

Main Technologies: PHP, Symfony, Silex, Go, Python, MySQL, ElasticSearch, Redis, Docker, AWS;

I was a member of a polyglot team responsible for developing and improving services aimed to build a car sharing platform. Most of the micro-services were developed using PHP with frameworks Symfony and Silex; however, there were also projects developed in Go and Python. All services were making use of AWS platform, such as ECS, SQS, ElasticCache, ElasticSearch, RDS and CloudWatch. In addition, I have developed a open source tool to make as easy as possible the continuous deployment. Testing was part of the company's culture, hands on PHPUnit, Prophesize and Behat for PHP projects, and for Go standard library was enough.

#### GIOX Tecnologia

Mar 2013 - Present

CEO and Full Stack Developer

Main Technologies: Go, PHP, JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3, MySQL, MongoDB, Docker, NSQ, Ansible, CoreOS, SOAP, XML;

As a entrepreneur I founded GIOX in 2013, a company focused in creating SaaS ERP for small businesses with electronic invoice (NF-e). The project was developed using mainly PHP as backend language with ZendFramework 2, Silex, Doctrine2 and PH-PUnit. MySQL was my choice for database and NSQ as message broker. Gradually as side project I've been migrating from the monolithic to microservices written in Go and using MongoDB. For the frontend I have used jQuery, Backbone.js, Underscore.js and Bootstrap3 frameworks, but also moving to more modern SPA using Vue.js, Firebase and Vuetify.

I built and deployed the whole infrastructure for GIOX ERP, as a result I improved myself as SysAdmin and DevOps. Now, the project is running on Digital Ocean and I make use of Ansible, Docker-compose, Docker Swarm, Git, Gitlab CI and Phing to automate tasks and maintain the Linux servers.

#### **Neoway Business Solution**

Jun 2015 - Sep 2016

Senior Backend Developer

Main Technologies: Go, ElasticSearch, MongoDB, RabbitMQ, Docker, Rkt, CoreOS, AWS;

Development of Big Data platform to Market Intelligence. I were using mainly Go but Node.js was also used in a couple of projects. I developed several RESTful API to communicate with different backends like: ElasticSearch, MongoDB and RabbitMQ which gave me some experience on how to use and configure them.

They loved DevOps culture there, for that I've developed some tools to automate our deploy at AWS. We often wrote unit and integration tests to make our deploy as continuous as possible using GitLab flow and Docker/Rkt containers.

#### uTech Tecnologia

Nov 2014 - Feb 2015

Full Stack Developer

Main Technologies: C++, Qt, QML, JavaScript, SIP;

Outsourced development of a Softphone to integrate with company's platform. The biggest challenge was be multi-platform, running in Windows 7, Linux and Mac OS X. The software was developed using C++, QML and JavaScript through Qt library and PJSIP as SIP stack.

# Digitro Tecnologia

Dec 2009 - Mar 2013

Backend Developer

Main Technologies: C, C++, Lua, SIP, uCLinux, GStreamer, ShellScript, Blackfin;

Embedded development of an IP Phone touch screen with color display using Blackfin processor with uCLinux distribution. We used u-boot, EFL graphic library, GLib, GObject, GDBus, CppUTest and Sofia-SIP as SIP stack.

Speaker recognition: Web service responsible for creating audio models from the voice and storing it. The voice models were used later to identify someone talking on a audio recording. Tools used: Lua, lighthttpd, GStreamer, fastcgi, MongoDB.

Keyword spotting: Middleware used to perform text search on audio using a proprietary protocol to communicate with clients. Tools used: Lua, C, GStreamer.

Flash Audio streaming server: Web service responsible for loading audio recordings in different audio codecs, transcode then, apply filters and effects and send to the client through the RTMP protocol. Tools used: C+++, C, GStreamer, Monit.

Skills Base

Programming Languages: Go, PHP, Python, JavaScript, C, C++, Lua and Java;

Databases: MongoDB, MySQL, Redis, ElasticSearch and basic of PostgreSQL;

Frameworks: Cobra, Silex, Symfony, ZendFramework2/3, Docktrine2, jQuery, Backbone.js, Underscore.js;

Agile practices: Kanban, SCRUM, Pair programming, Clean code, Code Review, TDD;

Tools: Git, Makefile, Ansible, GitLab CI, Kubernetes, Jenkins;

Languages: Fluent in Portuguese and English;

Others: RabbitMQ, NSQ, Docker, Docker-Compose, Rkt, AWS;

More Info

Linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/guilhermesilveirasantos

Github: https://github.com/guilherme-santos